I'm good
are you read because I've come to know
things and not shrinking back in
striving as one who does not shrink back
is driving nice truth when it comes a
stop phrase certainly let the skin
tendons and bones remain and let the
fish and the blood in the body dry off
sure for whatever can be obtained on
many strength efforts and exertion there
will not be a resting place for effort
oh so long as this has not been reached
not finding content in it yeah well II
but as long as you're not finding
content in wholesome phenomena means
you're still within the domain of
sensuality because the kind of one of
the defining traits of sensuality is to
expect things to provide you with
pleasure or rather pleasure is the result of
or rather pleasure is the result of
things you're engaged with but wholesome
states don't work like that
the ones that are not underlined by
answers and so on which means you can
stay with wholesome States all you want
but they won't provide you with pleasure
you need to discern the contentment it's
the same that's what we are so many go
to Janosz in regard to pleasure a
renunciation in regard to seclusion from
sensuality and that's like there is a
quite an important thing did you know
many people could probably recognize but
the practice of of meditation usually
revolves around replacing the pleasures
I'm used to with a new set of pleasures
with more peaceful more refined but
still expecting meditation to give you
the pleasure back but you get the
pleasure back only once you start
discerning it on the basis of wholesome
and that pleasure is pleasure it's not
underlined by the craving
which is the pleasure of sensuality so
having non contentment in wholesome
states means being still within the
sensuality even if you're perfectly
restrained it's still like belies the
attitude of restrained in order to yeah
get more yeah the attitude of expecting
things to do it to you so to speak my
history still yummy pleasure even if
it's like oh I expect no that's what
that's why it was that what was the
other one
yeah the Jonah yeah it was with you I
was speaking the theme the theme of
Jonah and we were said by by not
standing in mind in the theme of John
that you don't get the John by not
basically finding the pleasure in the
theme of renunciation you won't get it
John so you it's not just a question of
um renouncer than dancing and then jhana
happens to me you need to develop it
through that discernment of wholesome
the seminal seclusion the seminal
freedom freedom from that and although
simulated with the game but unless
that's done you won't happen to you
because whatever happens to you is gonna
be on account of sensuality so it seems
it's almost like obviously the better
describe to pleasure like the
blameworthy and the one that's not
blameworthy blameworthy being like
obviously it's something you pursue but
the nun blameworthy more like a
recognition is without that same
movement is it and that's we would say
you shouldn't fear that type of pleasure
because in the resulting wisdom like
will be the right view already that's
all you need really pleasure apart from
senses that's where also the neutral
feeling is pleasant when it's known when
there is a recognition of it you feel it
pleasantly when there isn't you feel it
painfully so the knowledge determines
how you feel it and you have to
basically through drilling learn how to start
through drilling learn how to start
appreciating it because of the habits of
the pool and sensuality and expectations
in the restraint
there's no ways there's sometimes this
kind of subtle notion that okay once
this is done once I'm done with this
restraining now I'll go back into the
normal thing yeah did you did I give you
that talk was he with you it was with
you abiding in on activity no he gave me the
abiding in on activity no he gave me the
one about thinking okay that's exactly
what talking about a body not activity
we're talking about big stuff oh yeah
although for him he was more like just
trying to highlight the state of footage
enough for him so he can kind of stop
doing it but the no this is more like
even people who necessarily whoo-hoo
there's this whole kind of assumption of
doing it and you need to suit their
Incirlik or abiding in non activity
which is always like it's definition of
jhana non activity but it's not just you
don't move your body it's known action
even by your mind as in thoughts come
and go thinking and pondering we talk
each we are but you are not doing it so
there is no intention towards action by
any outlet and then you learn to value
that as a state of peace as a state of
pleasure as a state of this passion and
you cultivate that any other habits of
sensuality that sotapanna Arisaka might
have had are gonna fade because once you
you you you sort of stand your mind in
the theme of that non activity not
needing to do anything and not doing
anything out of habit either like just
sit you're not doing John as either for
that matter
I'm doing my John and I know you're not
doing anything over it you don't get
distracted either cause even distraction
requires intentional giving in
requires you to do it to give it a push
but you're not doing even that so
clarity of mindfulness is the natural
result of it
no activity through any outlet of course
we can still say as you just mentioned
one can still move their body don't like
it paralyzed so it didn't but I'm I seem
to understand it as like like it's not
it on the level of like that taking up
of the intention which is called the
dupe which you're referring to as the
doing sure sure yeah the movement of the
body would be would be governed by the
artisan significance of often a reason
thing you need to go to toilet hunger
requires eating but you won't be doing
it that's it it's the the clarity of
mind from unshakable mindfulness not
because you're holding it so tightly
that he cannot shake it is because went
beyond things that shake so it's
unshakable
again thing about seam extent of the
danger sensuality because then you and
but then you have to discern the safety
in your non-engagement to accentuate
well is the safety is implied if you
read attorney the danger yeah well
that's the thing is the safety is
implied automatically because unless the
danger is discern you won't be looking
for safety because you don't feel you're
under threat that is how it works so you
make the effort to decide the danger
then immediately you are starting to
value sense of safety then yeah you
might in turn once you get the
recognition and start looking okay what
is the ultimate safety from it and then
focus on the safety as a theme but it
still then that safety is what sort of
implies the danger that you're trying to
get away from it's not like you fully
discern the danger okay and now I have
to go and figure out the safety from it
it's the full discernment of the danger
implies knowledge of safety already or
at least where the safety is the full
extent of sensuality is the full extent
of danger hmm seen the freedom yeah yeah
so if if you are if you are discerning
the the danger of sensuality you are
immediately kind of developing a
recognition of safety oh by trying to
develop a recognition of safety you
remind yourself of the danger of
sensuality either way you take one the
other one is doing and being developed
basically whichever we want to put first
it's fine
is seeing a safety renunciation science
is it seeing a safety in renunciation oh
yeah yeah it's like finding pleasure
Annunciation replacing the pleasures of
earnest pleasures of sensuality with
pleasure the renunciation but a mullah
talking about to the level of first
jhana whereby you surmount the whole
domain of sensuality through recognizing
that such eatery workers are armed safe
here that's already like a direct
insight based on the recognition of the
danger of sensuality but yeah of course
you wouldn't arrive a danger the
renunciation is a prerequisite you
wouldn't be able even to see the danger
sensuality if you haven't already been
taking on the renunciation restraint
seal up on faith okay yeah yeah sure
sure I saw were tremendous if the thing
is in if there's no safety and happiness
to be found another but the difference
the difference of I would sort of
highlight there is that if you truly see
the danger isn't reality you don't have
to do any renunciation your mind is
already giving it up by understanding
the danger of it that's what I was
trying to explain that's I think that's
what you meant to me the question that's
why the Buddha would say that they're
the full understanding of gratification
of the danger and the escape means the
full of it and then yeah that person
doesn't need to be renounced and we
would say because his behavior has been
developed beforehand as in the seal and
the virtue and so on so for as long as
somebody for as long as a person needs
to remind himself that all this is not
good means they're not free from their
domain it requires their action it
requires management it requires a
counterpart which is has to be that way
but what I'm encouraging is to while
you're doing that that'sthat's the talk
we had they wanted to give you while
you're doing that management and
reminders you
you want to find a place where it is
safe as in you don't have to defend it
because it's safe if something is safe
only if you go and fight back
it's not safe if you need to defend it
if you need to manager it if you need to
cover it if you need to pull it it's not
safe that's not definition of a high ground
that's not definition of a high ground
which cannot be flooded so that doesn't
mean you dismiss the renunciate the
abandon you were referring to this
abandonment yeah
doesn't mean you dismiss it but you want
to look past it even further
why are you doing it you want to find a
place where one required doing even that
and then you can say okay now I'm truly
safe because I don't even have to defend
it discerning essential domain because
yeah discerning the danger discerning
the extent of sensuality the extent of
its flood so to speak as a single
phenomena not like reminding yourself of
all the aspects that you've been through
yet that would equal safety like full
understanding of gratification full
understanding of danger means full
understanding of safety
so hers is saying that's you were saying
I think restraint is more primordial
than sensuality
that's basically what yeah so how do you
think it ties in well that's it because
you you have to you you do some mount
perceptions sensuality as a holla to
surmounted by discerning it that whole
domain could you only surmounted the
food stepping into a bigger phone but
why would it be more primordial
sorry ya mamas well because if you
weren't you wouldn't be able to summon
sensuality you wouldn't be able to free
yourself from it and also what we spoke
before because things are in the nature
first a super because of the
impermanence because of the the non
satisfaction and so on so any notion of
sensuality is literally plastered over
it while it's still that the Super's
there so in the same very restraint
reveals it reveals it reveals the actual
repulsive aspect even of attractive
things hence restraint reveals what's
more primordial and restrained is more
primordial or puts in touch with what's
first not what second which sensuality
but of course you wouldn't arrive there
without the restraint just being done
first you have to say no to it you don't
know why you don't know how it hurts but
the Buddha said there is no done without
sila so you just start doing it but
you're not doing it for its own sake
you're doing it so to see so that you
can stop doing it but then of course you
will be it so you won't have to you
won't be stopping anything basically it
will be a natural mode of behavior
nonsense reality and restraint because
if if the repulsive aspect of sensual
things is not actually more fundamental
than sensuality freedom from society
will not be possible because you you you
can't fabricate you don't create the
down on top of things like there was
nothing the way is out you need to
discern it as we said the past is there
you need to find it and that part
wouldn't be there if repulsive is not
more fundamental than attractive that's
just how things are ordered and that's
what you're supposed to discern and
that's how you get free from sensuality
not by deciding and saying no to it
their sexualities fabricated well it is
but I want to say that because then
people think okay all I have to do stop
stop thinking about my sensuality and
that's why I'm fabricated censured is a
view it's it's a summary to padana which
means the distortion is there and it's
real as such for you as the greatest a
diversion of perception
yeah from arahants point of view it's an
inversion to to jinnah state is an
inversion it's like second putting first
first put in second but Putrajaya that's
what the own view he has so he has no
reference point but first what second so
unless he sees that rightly in other
words unless he abandons it he won't see
you rightly so that's why you have to he
has to start with that as a starting
point he can't say oh well this sensuality is
he can't say oh well this sensuality is
secondary and and the non-centrality is
first because he doesn't see either so
he needs to start sensualities first for
me it's a mistake but until I undo that
mistake that is my form of existence
that is my bar that is the extent of my
Bala the central being you see what I
mean in that sense it's more primordial
yes entropy because it reveals the more
primordial order basically yeah I mean
being literally means the extent of your
being
like there's more where you can see it
there's more non attraction generally
what you don't notice that I mean you
might notice that but in order for it to
play part in Reverse reverting back the
inversion of sensuality you need to see
it in the same sense when we started
speaking about the tits and father the
same principle you need to see the
simultaneously present and determining
your sensuality if you see left to right
from it it's a second thing you can't
compare it in the same sense your whole
life you're speaking talking walking
eating depends on your beating heart
that you're now saying in the same sense
your central project central attraction
central view central craving sensual
pleasures depend upon presence of things
that are actually repulsive simultaneous
presence not after it's not that ugly
becomes really beautiful while you're
with the beautiful in its heart it's
ugly but you're not seeing that
relationship between that heart and what
you're looking at and that's why you're
not free from it that's we can look old
a super pictures you want oh you can
look at one but if you see the right
principle then you know then it's like a
super Namita as in you you did you
recognize peripherally discern that
signs of our that's where our super is
you found a place for it but it's not
just another object of your eyes and and
and and smell and so on
whereby a will not look ad ugly I will
not look at the beautiful I will look at
the ugly but I'm still looking and I'm
still not understanding the nature of
sight sound smell taste touch the host
and show domain you're not understanding
you're just replacing the objects of
your eyes basically fairly to understand
the nature of it so in that sense yeah
you can like which is more ugly or
beautiful in the world just go in the
town which is more ugly people or
beautiful people okay non attractive
that is the basis for everything but if
you see it in a comparative manner
it's almost like an information makes no
difference but if you see there's a
basis upon which beautiful exists to the
extent that the basis determines it then
okay because you can't have the
principle of inversion unless the two
things that are inverted simultaneously
inversion is not one than the other it's
one and two inversion is what's first
it's second what second its first while
both are still there that's a definition
of inversion my solar inverter it
inverts the electricity that comes to another
the electricity that comes to another
electricity that you can use
simultaneous if the electricity that
comes disappears there is an inversion
anymore so you need to have two things
for that you just have to stop mixing
the order of go super to Aegina or
somebody's not to free from central
being first is beautiful beautiful is
first but you won't find ugly as second
you need to find it within the heart of
that first beautiful without abandoning
first is beautiful you need to see its
foundations are actually fully dependent
determined rooted in the ugly the
repulsive and that's how you that's how
it it stops being ugly and beautiful it
becomes really ugly and slightly less
ugly but all its repulsive all of it
that's where the similar principle but
that's what I think might be sorry puto
the Buddha said pleasure counts as pain
in the discipline of the noble ones
sorry Buddha pleasure counts as pain and
pain counts like an deadly arrow as in
it so bad
but it it so bad but doesn't pertain to
anymore because you abandoned it so it's
not like that you need to be like oh
it's so bad so what what I was saying is
fabricating know it is yeah sure
I agree but as I qualified it you don't
want to say that because usually implies
are fabrication you know I'm fabricating
you now all I need to do is stop
fabricating it no all you need to do is
uproot that thing then you won't be able
to fabricate centrality even if you want
to because you are proved to the
inversion that's why the firaon egami
not hunt it's not a matter of choice
that they can engage in central behavior
it's the state of their being like some
Cara like fabricating the condition
reality yeah that's a minute oh I heard
even more flamboyant translation than
that I have anything because of
ignorance fabrication is like it's
already there that's the whole thing all
of it is already there for petitioner he
needs to reverse the order uh Norma
party Lola part of the same things I was
trying to mean what it was that I've
noticed that when beautiful what I
considered to be beautiful start to
become ugly I would try to look
beautiful in that show because the
version principle is where you act from
that's the assumption that's that's
basically the central loop Adana exactly
that what your experience is actually
showing you ugly left and right yet you
keep discerning only beautiful within it
because that's all you see
but that you're doing that's what I
would have said the beautiful things in
the world are not sensuality it's your
thought and lust in regard to it that
man's sensuality is there L should do it
yeah exactly it's not super is not
you're doing a superb its recognition
that undermines your own doing of
sensuality and then you can't do it bad in order to
and then you can't do it bad in order to
fully under man you need to start this
thing the danger in which you were doing
or what you want to do because if you
don't you're still going to be attracted
to it yeah but exactly yeah it's it's a
form of doing in the level we spoke
about not like you know doing speaking
beliefs or something it doesn't even on
a mental level
I had something related to this kind of
like I was I was thinking you know a
teacher some product with this this is I
thought I thought it was referring to
the principle of whatever I attend it is
with something else a background to the
attention so to say but I think in light
of this conversation I may have we've
had some confusion I think because
potentially I was over prioritizing the
attention given to like sense perception
like it seems to me the idea that when I
attend something I think the unavenged
it like nothing like the mind as subject
can attend he called him like universals
natures of things though to speak
because I was confused but my definition
because I could say being I can't like I
can't Dom be this and being like I
attend stuffy room so how I got in in
light of my paradigm how is it then that
I would discern its dependence on
assumption well first just when you say
when you attend something then Daddy
but it's and father would be that thing
you're attending is determined by
something else that's true as a
principle but in practice that thing
that determines what you're attending is
behind your attention so to speak as in
it's not something you can also attend
because if you do you make it into
another thing I'm insisting on this
because if you start attempting it needs
to see that is you cannot not include
yourself in that experience in other
words it ceases to be abstract pondering
with this this you are part of that
picture your experience right here right
now it's part of what you're trying to
understand because if I'm attending at
this and it's determined by something
else that I cannot attend it
simultaneously there which is behind my
attention as in I can't rest okay so
what is that thing because if I attend
to it it's behind its behind from the
direction of your attention so what's
behind its that peripheral that I'll
talk about it you can discern so I'll
attend the cup you can see there is
feeling president there is intention
present without you know stopping your
attention to the cup you see there's a
decision present their views present
basically but if you look at them
directly they become a new thing which
means something else is them peripheral
to it so you can't have it both to the
same extent so it's perfectly fine to
contemplate that principle on the level
of senses what you refer to in terms of
the being and the more refined ways of
the same principle will be once you just
fully discerning the peripheral in
regard to attending then you can attend
to that peripheral in that non attentive
manner so to speak indirectly because
that's what means like obtaining jhanas
at will but you know exactly where they
are in relation to establishing your
mind and you can't establish them just
your perception through looking or doing
something but because you became so
skilled in discerning the peripheral
domain of mindfulness you could just
literally attend it in that indirect
manner and that's it in the same manner
and kind of say like you can see it
without having to look at it that's what
I'm talking about so the more you
practice that the more you get to see
without having to attend it and look at
it directly and that's that's what I
mean the problem of patina and the
notion of is being is it's real what I
can look what I can perceive the problem
of method what I can do which means for
as long as he focused on the content or
what he's perceiving he's not going to
see the nature of it and nature is that
peripheral area further that's why the
Buddha said knowledge comes off the
perception of course you can understand
that you collect the information on
perception then you figure out the
knowledge but you can also understand it
in a simultaneous manner it's after like
this is perceived and it's all over
based on that but it's not it knowledge
is not the perception it comes after
recognize of being yes yes but you won't
recognize it if you start thinking oh I
should be recognizing the phenomena
being it's discerned yes and then the
information you have about what you're
supposed to discern it's gonna be
recognized and so if you dwell on the
principle sufficiently enough you start
discerning okay that's what that's what
it means but if you take it as an object
of okay the being must reckon is pretty
even worth like that that is that is the
level of abstract that's the difference
yeah exactly yeah that's all the
problems of the Western classical and ru
Sencha philosophy they just there's no
being without thinking but you can't
think you're being from from deck it is
to solder and they couldn't figure it
out because they took the sense of self
for granted but without thinking you
wouldn't be well it determines each
other basically thinking means you are
you are because you think it's a it's a
valid recognition of of despotism and
others but now you need to that's what
of Dhamma stance that that's where the
philosophy ended they couldn't go
further than that but that's what now it
begins that's where Dhamma goes beyond
its article Chara you can't think it in
that sense doesn't mean it's mystical
means it's not on the level of reasoning
and logic cuz that already is secondary
to the beam
let's get back to practical - matters
because all this would be extension of
the same thing I'm talking about but you
don't need to either need to go to it
through the philosophical ponderings can
we clarify that the notion that for me
when you asked about potential father
like you can think in that manner and
you could say yes correct according to
principle but to some extend you're
leaving yourself out as in your sense of
self right here right now in this
experience as a whole it's not included
don't have it included is to start
discerning the peripheral that's
peripheral to your sense of self as well
not just to the object of your attention
so then you will you will force yourself
to be included which means then any
discernment any understanding it happens
will happen on that level and it will be
measured by the feeling in absence of
dukkha it's done rightly because again
it's not that you make understanding of
impermanence and on control pleasurable
or or or resulting in freedom that's
just how things things are if things
were not truly impermanent again freedom
from suffering would not be possible but
they are truly permanent something
freedom from suffering as possible but
only for those who discerned it
and that's what I mean like the measure
of your understanding is inability to
suffer until you become completely an
arrogant of course by which time I mean
you will be quite quite certain and
quite confident in it but even before
aren't you the absence of suffering now
because you're avoiding it because
you're managing it now because you're
very skilled in managing no because not
nothing challenges you but because
you're unable to suffer amid suffering
suffering becomes inconceivable
you don't need to do anything I can't do
it because he didn't touch you in the
first place well we spoke a couple weeks
ago Viera you don't grieve you don't
lament because you didn't touch in the
first place
but that didn't touch in the first place
it's not an accident it's not something
you stumble upon or something that
happened to you something you discerned
you discern the place where he won't
touch you in the first place
suffering hence whatever is to be
obtained by man their foot manly
reflection manly this man is our thing
that's what it would it would say it's
not given it's not it hasn't occurred oh
I just experienced must mean up free
from suffering
going back into the first seat to hear
it the other counter part of it was that
you know that was an unremitting effort
oh yeah well then DAC like I mean I
don't know how people individually thing
but based on what I've seen whenever
this past it'll be quoted people would
perceive unremitting effort means I
determine it I determine it so hard then
I'll never give it up but it's not it's
not it's not the result of your will and
volition it's a result of your
understanding that establishes your mind
into the unwavering effort and then you
know yeah my seniors can go whatever
after one sees in the same sense a monk
would establish his mind upon the
perception in the forest then go to the
village whatever happens in the village
doesn't know about his mind because his
mind is established upon the creative
perception so establish a mind upon a
perception of unwavering effort it's
earn it as an independent phenomena
independent of your doing because
whatever is the nature arising as the
nature seizing means whatever has a
nature arising has a reason
independently of your sense of self
including your very effort so yeah you
need to do it first in order to discern
it as a phenomenon and if you do then
that unremitting effort is effortless
you're not doing it the only reason you
thought you were doing it because you
thought you could do it
now this as long as the pretty much [Music]
and glad you explained it like that
because I think effort in particular is
a hard thing to grasp it something
you're not doing in the same way we've
been speaking about they're doing mmm
yeah sure but yeah that's true you just
kind of anyway speaking find yourself
efforting and way of speaking I guess
you could say you bring your mind to it
well if you start losing the losing this
the perception of the phenomenon of
effort enduring that's where you learn
without will you see our eyes energy for
the only reason holds of states but once
they're there you know home Rosie no now
they're there
let them in you because you established
it that's how you establish the mind
and how long it lasts that's not up to
you that's pretty much predetermined by
the clarity of your discernment and and
that effort no pun intended
that's what I said in that was a jewel
available about the jhana mrs. Holly
among who doesn't think I'm about to
taint John Rama I'm getting into John
his mind gets set beforehand established
and then the John is established and it
lasts for as long as that previous sort
of his setup has determined it to last
it's not after him arousal eventually
yes but you gotta go through some pain
off like you know saying no to the
unwholesome and so on like having to and
you the discrepancy say no to the pole
but yeah once you start ascending that
is a phenomena then it becomes
effortless fun like in the in the
ultimate sense from our hands point of
view it's effortless but as I said
petitioner starts from the other end and
that is his reality so it's gonna take
some like actual doing of saying no
withstanding things saying no to the
poor and so on but again doing it for
its own sake won't result in any
liberation but doing it and then
understanding the nature of that doing
that that can result and then it becomes
effortless then you're not doing it then
you're not doing silanol your duty of
the month it's not done it's there but
you're not doing it so see how about the
part of masters gone do you really want
to develop that say I think that's what
we recorded pretty much when they I was
making the same things in that like non
activity yeah I was thinking that's what
yeah yes the foot actually like this
unremitting effort sounds pretty much on
the same level as no not dude it is yeah
you descend on activity correctly that
is effortless but your state is the
state of established
but you need to establish something
until it takes root until it takes place
then you don't have to because it's
there
it seems to me almost like if it
described it as indirect so to speak
like it's not like you clench your fists
necessarily but more like by refraining
and you know doing that effort of
restraining good mother arousing any any
any discernment of the phenomena it's
it's pretty much indirect you can't
attend to it as you said you kind of
tend to the being of a thing you can
discern it so but once you start
asserting that that is you realize well
it's it it's directly indirect basically
it's direct knowledge of the indirect
way so you have to go through the
indirect motions that will result into
it that's only the beginning because
you're looking at the wrong place like
against the grain is in direct from with
the grain of patina but once against the
grain becomes your mode of being that's
the direct mode of being and you abandon
do with the grain that's that's why the
result of that discernment is
abandonment of these things as in you
can't okay you know I'm origami I had a
good time now I want to go back and do
what we did you know it becomes it's
abandoned because the other way became
your mode of being and it's irreversible
why because ignorance was never supposed
to be there
he's beginningless but there is no first
point from which ignorance wasn't and
then it became as goodness to himself so
once you undo it we cannot take root
again
today there is a slight movie of
abandonment in restrain well if you
understand the nature of restraint
without understanding it won't happen by
accident understanding can't happen by accident
I see he flirting is better
well no he's a form of abandonment just
not not not a complete form do you want
to be aiming at no of course it's full
of abandonment